<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bayesian on Sau-Chin Chen&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>/en/tags/bayesian/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bayesian on Sau-Chin Chen&#39;s Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Sau-Chin Chen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/en/tags/bayesian/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>If Emily Rosa met Thomas Bayes ...</title>
      <link>/en/post/if-emily-rosa-met-thomas-bayes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/if-emily-rosa-met-thomas-bayes/</guid>
      <description>Twenty years ago 11-years-old Emily Rosa and her parents publsihed their study in Journal of the American Medical Association. This study was designed by Emily herself two years before the publication. Before 1998, Therapeutic Touch (commonly shortened to “TT”) had been advocated in hundreds of hospitals and nursing schools in North America. Forty thousands of health care professionals had been trained to use TT for their patient. The trained TT professionals were claimed, by the promoters, have the skill to manipulate the energy field surrounded human body without touching.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autopsy of NHST and Bayesian Models (part 1)</title>
      <link>/en/post/2016-04-30-autopsy-of-nhst-and-bayesian-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/2016-04-30-autopsy-of-nhst-and-bayesian-models/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 2 of Statistical Rethinking: A Bayesian Course with Examples in R and Stan introduces a water tossing example for the demonstration how Bayesain model run through the data based on the researcher’s hypothesis. This chapter defines a three stage process that are used in the coming chapters. We start from a narrated Data Story, then update the models by filling data in, and finally evaluate all the upated models.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>