<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R_programming on Sau-Chin Chen&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>/en/tags/r_programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R_programming on Sau-Chin Chen&#39;s Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Sau-Chin Chen</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/en/tags/r_programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Use bookdownplus write papers and manage lab logs</title>
      <link>/en/post/use-bookdownplus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/use-bookdownplus/</guid>
      <description>Since being a Rmarkdown user, I’m thinking how to write papers, manage teaching materials and record lab works in this format. When I met papaja(Aust and Barth 2017) three years ago, it is my dream someday I will use R(R Development Core Team 2010) process all my works. papaja is amazing but it is implemented to English only. Later I found bookdown developed by Yihui Xie(Xie 2017). bookdown has the potential to manage Chinese writings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethink Significance</title>
      <link>/en/post/2016-05-05-rethink-significance/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/2016-05-05-rethink-significance/</guid>
      <description>To trace the fallacy of use hypothesis testing, I am programming the examples in Dr. Adrianus D. de Groot’s paper The meaning of “signiﬁcance” for different types of research. This paper is published in 1956 in the Dutch journal Nederlands Tijdschrift voor de Psychologie en Haar Grensgebieden. Adrianus De Groot is Dutch psychologist and chess master. During 1950s and 1960s, he suggested the concept of emperical cycle for the researchers who use the statistical tools in the social and behavioral researches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Check My Tools to Create and Manipulate Golems</title>
      <link>/en/post/2016-04-22-check-my-tools-to-create-and-manipulate-golems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/2016-04-22-check-my-tools-to-create-and-manipulate-golems/</guid>
      <description>Since two weeks before I published this post, I have started read the book Statistical Rethinking: A Bayesian Course with Examples in R and Stan written by Richard McElreath. Richard is the evolutionary anthropologist at Max Planck Institute. He wrote this textbook for the PhD students who will use the Bayesian statistics in their research projects. Compared to the textbooks written by statisians and data scientistst, Richard’s book explain and demonstrate the statistical methods with examples instead of equations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vectors in mathematics and in codes</title>
      <link>/en/post/2016-04-05-vectors-in-mathematics-and-in-codes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/2016-04-05-vectors-in-mathematics-and-in-codes/</guid>
      <description>When a set of data/observations is imported to R, it is usually treated as vector. Vector has two mathematical forms as following:
column vector:
\[ \vec{a} = \begin{bmatrix}1\\2\\3\\\end{bmatrix} \]
row vector:
\[ \vec{a} = [ 1\ 2\ 3 ] \]
Default form of vector in R is column vector. More precisely, it is treated as a matrix:
a &amp;lt;- 1:3a## [1] 1 2 3class(a)## [1] &amp;quot;integer&amp;quot;str(a)## int [1:3] 1 2 3t(a)## [,1] [,2] [,3]## [1,] 1 2 3In a statistical work, we used to calcuate the sum of square (SS) for the deviations to mean.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning Sampling Distribution in R Programming</title>
      <link>/en/post/2016-03-30-learning-sampling-distribution-in-r-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/en/post/2016-03-30-learning-sampling-distribution-in-r-programming/</guid>
      <description>Sampling distribution is the set of possible outcomes when we collect data through the randomization procedure (random sampling, ramond assignment). Do a simulation work is the best way to understand the sampling distribution. A simulation work is unrelated to any context we collect the data. You can connect the simulation work to any randominzation in the real world.
In this pseudo experiment, there are only ten observations we will collect in every sample.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>